yeah, I don't know if anyone noticed, but
things go wrong all the time.
Anyone ever broken production?
instead of kind of identifying things that individuals did wrong.
we focus on processes that allow these situations
to arise in the first place.
Oh, no. Oh!
So I'm going to be discussing
how we built a rich text editor incident, for writing post-mortems.
But before I kind of get into that, I'll, add some context about what instant
IO does,
what postmortems are, and how all these things kind of relate to each other.
So, yeah, a bit about me. My name's Merlin.
I actually come from a design background originally and accidentally
found my way into tech.
Some sort of a front end leaning product engineer.
Some career highlights for me.
Co-founded and led engineering, mode at work,
which was recently acquired by Ukg.
I was an early employee at Samir, which was kind of a rag
for investment research, which is backed by Eric Schmidt.
Yes. Since
September, I found myself at incident, which I'm very much enjoying.
And shout out to Will, who helped me
get the job there. So,
So, yeah,
I don't know if anyone noticed, but things go wrong all the time.
Anyone ever broken production?
Good to see some.
Some hands go up there.
Yeah, the consequences can be quite big.
And I think as we're just looking at, like,
AI has really increased the rate of change.
And while in some cases, these feedback loops
might kind of help lower the change failure rate.
Yeah.
When you're kind of five zoom
or ten, increasing the, amount of changes you're making.
The situation is probably getting worse in terms of things going wrong.
These things may be familiar to you.
There's a fairly well known instance from the last few years as CrowdStrike
where like, a routine update,
caused millions machines to crash worldwide means that the systems
are fleeing from a cyber incident, meaning they couldn't take any orders.
And that was for weeks, I think.
And maybe hundreds of millions in lost profit.
Yeah.
And then TfL had a major outage as well.
These are all kind of completely different companies,
different tech stacks.
But in all three cases, you know, something breaks and suddenly a lot
is at stake.
Customers, money, reputation, regulation kind of all at once.
And these are incidents, but on a smaller scale,
we kind of deal with smaller versions of these on a fairly regular basis.
And on the inside, you know,
we see these kind of headlines in the news that these really are serious things.
But there's often, you know, there's poor engineers
who are kind of dealing with these disasters as they happen.
You can imagine it's 2 a.m., your phone's going off.
You join a call half awake.
You know, it's something bad.
There's alerts firing everywhere.
There's, like, three other people on the call,
and they've all got completely different theories.
No one's got the full picture.
And you're forced to make decisions
about how you're going to act with, you know, a fraction of the information
that you actually need to do a proper decision.
Every minute kind of feels expensive in that situation.
The longer it goes on, the worse the impact.
You're trying to think clearly.
For knowing thousands,
if not millions of users can be affected by, your decisions.
This is the worst case scenario. But, like,
this does apply to, like, even smaller incidents.
So, yeah, incidents I think are inevitable.
But the chaos doesn't have to be.
So instant io.
We're building an end to end platform for incident response and management.
So this includes, like, several products that will work together.
So we have our own core product, and this is about making sure
that the right person's phone makes a horrible noise at 3 a.m.
and gets them up and out of bed.
And allows those people to also escalate to the right people to get into the room.
Our response product, which kind of turns
slack or teams into an incident command centre,
allowing people to clearly communicate and delegate tasks to each other.
And our AI as a product, which is all about
kind of kickstarting this incident investigation.
To find out what the root causes, even before you've joined the slack channel.
So by the time you get there, you've got a decent context of what's gone wrong.
And it can also automate some of the resolution steps for you as well.
And then finally, status pages product, which is all about
keeping customers and end users informed about what's going on.
So yeah, this is where we are today as a company.
We, 180 people.
We've just in fact, today hit, 700,000
incidents across our customers. Who,
although I do feel sorry for them, said I don't want to celebrate too much.
Yes.
We've got about 1500 customers.
Headquarters and all.
Our product engineering is based out of London, just by Old Street roundabout.
And then in New York
and San Francisco, we've got that go to market and sales teams.
We do work with, amazing customers.
Might be some logos that you recognise as well as some of London's
hottest Start-Ups as well.
So yeah.
So this talk is going to be about post mortem.
So like, where does that fit into all of this stuff? So,
things don't necessarily finish when the incident resolved
and the dust is settled, there's debrief meetings.
We create and track followup tasks, and postmortems
are like a really key part of what happens after an incident.
They let you create, like, a record of events.
They're kind of a reflection exercise,
on what has happened and opportunity for learning.
They help you identify what the true root cause was.
And document any, like, preventative measures and changes you're going to make.
And the key part of postmortems is that they should be blameless.
So instead of kind of identifying things that individuals did wrong.
Instead we focus on processes or like lack of guardrails
that allow these situations to arise in the first place.
Okay, cool.
So we know what a post-mortem is.
This talk is about creating a modern writing experience.
So we'll try and define that as well.
I might be showing my age a bit
here, but like, sometimes it's easier to define things in opposition.
So we're going looking at some things which are not modern writing experiences.
Anyone remember this?
So yeah, like rich text.
I think when we used to think about rich text,
it used to be this kind of almost infinite styling options.
You could pick from lots of fonts, you pick some colours, sizes,
and now I think really
when we talk about rich text, it's about like being data rich.
It's dynamic.
It's embedded content.
Clutter free.
So this I think, in old versions of word, you could install all these
extra power toolbars to allow you to do stuff.
And yeah, I think we used to think of this
as empowering people with all these controls,
but I think now we've realised less is more.
And the job of software is to facilitate focus,
focus on the content and writing.
And additionally, I think UI concepts such as progressive disclosure and adaptive
interfaces have kind of helped replace this sort of clutter that we get here.
Yeah.
Multi-player.
I've worked places
before where we've had to send files back and forth over email.
And take it in turns of who's going to edit it.
Or if you're lucky enough to have a server to have all your files
on, then they would get locked
and you only one person could be looking at it at a time.
And I think in modern applications, the idea of like real time
collaboration is just table stakes.
And it's what everyone expects.
I native so this is it's
not really fair on Clippy because Cliffie wasn't actually like an AI product.
I think it was just a very long list of regexes.
But it was this idea of having a writing assistant, which in some ways
was kind of ahead of its time, but it was, fairly unanimously, people decided
that it was very annoying and distracting and not an experience that we wanted.
So now when we think about, like how AI weaves itself into products,
like it's not this sort of bolted on thing,
it's kind of integral to how the product works.
Its magic kind of sprinkled through various touchpoints.
Along the journey.
So yeah, why why bother
building one, incident II why why are we building a text editor?
I think we own the kind of whole
incident process, and we have all the data,
and we really feel this, like, makes us the best, best place
to kind of eliminate the busywork that comes with post-mortems.
I mean, yeah,
we have all the context for documents to be truly rich.
You can kind of mention and embed kind of a lot of things inside an incident
post-mortem doc, various services or apps that you might be in control and control
of, teams in your company, your customers pull requests,
conversations from slack, other incidents,
and over time, like building a corpus of,
like, rich incident data compound's value.
This data is used by humans,
but also increasingly AI to kind of spot common patterns and themes.
And is helped by, ISV product to help diagnose issues
when we can see that something has happened before
in a previous incident, with similar patterns that might be,
you know, the root cause to to a new incident.
And finally, we think
investing time into making postmortems
as good as possible helps create less incidents.
And we're while we are developing tools, I guess.
Sorry, to help resolve incidents faster.
Like, nothing is quicker than just avoiding it in the first place.
So yeah, a really strong post-mortem where you've identified
what the true root cause is and like sufficient
follow up measures to kind of stop the incident happening again.
We'll save you a lot of time in the long run.
So in terms of the project, this is, where we are at the moment.
So, we started this back in August.
We did a demo of it, sev zero conference in San Francisco in September.
In October, we basically had to make the demo actually work because there was
a lot of kind of smoke and mirrors in terms of what we demoed there.
We got this in the hands of an early access group in November,
and there's quite a lot of integration work at that point to kind of build it
into our platform rather than kind of a standalone demo.
In December, this hit general availability.
And we were running this in parallel to our old editor
experience, which then in January we kind of killed that off.
So that was
just sort of one experience in the app.
Currently we, in February and we're kind of working on Delight and Polish,
which is kind of a series of smaller but awesome new features
and kind of iterating on the feedback that we've got from customers so far.
And we're gearing up to marketing launch, next month.
So, I'm looking forward to that.
We're going to have some videos out.
Catch them.
Probably been on LinkedIn.
We have to find those.
So. Yeah.
How do we build it?
Yeah. We know what an incident is.
Now we know what a post-mortem is.
We know what a modern writing experience is.
And why we're building one.
So let's look into the how,
I think it's probably
best to start this by saying, like, rich text editors are a hard problem.
The content editor API has got a lot of rough edges.
Managing selection state in the browser is a bit of a pain
and doesn't like neatly fit into React's way of seeing the world.
And real time collaboration is a hard problem.
I'd also say like, these aren't really
like problems that we have an interest in owning.
So we're very, like, happy to kind of lean on open source tools where we can.
So we're mainly using, tip top, which is a
we sort of see it as a headless developer experience
glue layer around, kind of several other key open source components.
Pros mirror, which is one that's kind of the core of the editor.
It handles schemas, change management, stuff like that.
Y JS which is this conflict free replicated data type?
This is what's used for real time collaboration allows,
multiple people to edit a document at once.
You can sort of think of it like get for documents,
but the sort of difference to chain is like you never get merge conflicts.
It's got like, an algorithm that will always merge to some state,
rather than kind of having to manually resolve those conflicts.
Hocus pocus, which is tip tops, collaboration server,
which wraps up tools like, watch s
markdown it which we use for like markdown parsing and transforming
and link ify which detects links, hashtags, mentions stuff like that.
And I think also kind of in
this process it's worth mentioning, UX inspiration as well.
Like we talk about like what open source tools to be used.
But I think we're very happy to kind of lean on
like UX and UI patterns that we see in other tools that we really like.
And when we think they're relevant, we're we're happy to borrow those.
So yeah, we'll do a,
bit of a deep, deep dive into tip top.
So I think the there's a core part of tip top is schemas.
They're at the heart of pros.
And you can sort of think of them as like strictly defining
what is valid content for your document.
So yeah, everything is a plugin.
There's plenty of off the shelf plugins.
Tip tap has their own starter kit full of stuff.
And you can build your own.
We built lots for ourselves,
but you can sort of think of every single thing that can belong in your document.
Is a plugin.
Nodes are a key part of this.
So these are like content types
you can think of like headings and paragraphs will be nodes in your document.
But yeah, we built lots of custom nodes for stuff
like our timeline, and tracking follow up tasks all within the document
marks. Yeah.
Bold, italic, strikethrough.
You can sort of think of them as styling.
Inline styling.
But this can also include stuff like highlighting comments, inline code.
And then decorations.
These are kind of interesting
because they're not persisted or synced as part of your document.
They sort of just live on your machine
locally, for a short amount of time.
So we might use this for draft comments before you submit a comment.
A comment, but you want to highlight a part in the document.
Or suggested I changes in inserting links where you want to select the text
and then decide where that's linking to those kind of temporary
states are all handled by decorations.
And I think it's also worth
pointing out that the schema, isn't one file.
It's kind of collated from all the various plugins
that you pass into your editor.
And yeah, the other novelty about,
Tic TAC is, is this interoperability between HTML and Json.
The kind of the document can be represented in.
And this is mainly to enable copy and paste.
So it sort of lives on the clipboard as HTML.
But lives kind of in the browser stay as Json.
And it's slightly confusing that the HTML representation
that you specify isn't necessarily what you actually get in the browser,
like react is used to render it, but you also define what each node,
what will live,
will look like when it's on the clipboard.
So yeah, let's,
jump into some code of what this might look like.
So this is I'll use a mention node.
I'm sure you've all seen user mentions and stuff,
so you can kind of imagine what that might look like.
Yeah.
We'll say this is an inline node.
So it sits within, say, a paragraph.
And it's an atom, which in prose
Mario world basically means that you can't set your cursor inside it.
You can delete the whole thing
at once or add the whole thing at once, but you can't edit the the middle bit.
Here
we have to pass each HTML and render each HTML functions for the node.
And this basically instructs it how to, when you want to copy
everything to the clipboard, it will kind of yeah, render it into HTML.
And when you're pasting back into the editor it will say
how to turn the HTML back into, Json.
And then those attributes, your node can contain various attributes.
You kind of think of these like props in react.
These get persisted with the document.
And for each one of these you will have like, pass
and render method as well.
This part is where we kind of hand off to react.
So in our application, react actually handles how we want to render these.
And finally there's this, add HTML
schema awareness where each node you can add this description of how
this should behave, how you create one in kind of natural language.
And these are used to pass to an alarm.
So if an alarm is kind of co editing your document,
it knows how to do so.
It's a quick
look at, collaboration architecture.
So yeah, we've, we sort of fetch a token from our API.
We have a self-hosted, collaboration server
that we run in our own infrastructure.
And that has WebSocket connection
for, like, two way sync between various browsers.
And the collaboration server.
And then the collaboration server, like, lazily syncs
with our API and our Postgres as a sort of backup for that.
And as I said earlier, we're
using like, watches for this,
why this is kind of interesting.
So like, you can update any replica independently and concurrently
without having to coordinate with any of the other replicas.
It automatically resolves any inconsistencies.
And the replicas may have a different state
at any particular point in time, but like, they are eventually consistent.
Yeah.
And then we're gonna talk a little bit about AI native experience. So,
We, yeah, we kind of have this sort of like, deep
incident context that sort of goes into, AI.
So we have all, like, our alert state, telemetry,
ASV investigations, slack conversations, or like, messages, links, images,
scribe transcripts, which is, kind of,
meeting transcriber, the incident
timeline, the people involved, any updates that have been issued?
And this allows us to kind of
create a, like an initial draft of the post-mortem document.
Allows us to redraught it and kind of rewrite certain sections.
Reviewing of the document,
to find inaccuracies, conflicting information and missing follow ups.
And yeah, it's also useful for scribe our kind of meeting
transcriber and note taker.
So, yeah, we, going to do demo time
and was also pointing out that, yeah, we are hiring.
So come chat to mail.
Meg, if you want to find out more about that.
See if this works.
So, yeah, this is, text editor.
You can kind of see a list of collaborators online.
We can go into focus mode.
These are some of the mentions where you kind of get a lot of context about,
things within our organisation.
This is our timeline,
where you can see all the things that happened in an incident.
You can create tables here.
I'm just tidying this up.
We have links to pull requests.
You can find out a bit more about those.
We have a, like, a slash menu, so you can create content,
without leaving the keyboard.
We support drag and drop for image uploads.
Here you can see we have, ask
AI feature where you can highlight parts of the document,
and ask our AI agent to explain them or give you a review on them.
So in this case, we want to find out a bit more
about these two pull requests and what they actually did.
This would be working in the background.
I can carry on working on different parts of the document,
adding a follow up task here.
Always need some more unit tests.
And hey,
I've got my answer back from our agent of, Yeah.
What was included in those two pull requests?
There we go.
That's kind of a brief, brief look at what we built.
So, yeah.
That's it.
Happy to take any questions.
Thank you very much.
Oh, no. Oh!